Immaculate A. Nyaugo

Nutrition Manager – MOH Nutrition and dietetics Unit. Manager Agri-Nutrition & Coordinator Kenya National Food Consumption Survey.

KEY QUALIFICATIONS

Immaculate is an accomplished public health and Nutrition professional with two decades of experience in human nutrition, Agri-nutrition, environmental hygiene and sanitation. I have a proven track record of working within Public sector supporting development of Nutrition Plans, Policies, guidelines, strategies and Frameworks which guides nutrition projects' implementation. In addition, I have supported the execution of USAID-funded projects in Health and nutrition, Agriculture and nutrition, Food security, Water resource management, Hygiene and sanitation. As Project Advisor, I advised a multi-year projects, while developing organization-wide good nutrition practices, including establishing strategic health and nutrition plans for projects and training in-country staff. I have focused on multi-sectoral coordination approach and partner development, and have built the capacity of civil society organizations in Kenya on nutrition related issues. Immaculate has extensive experience providing comprehensive nutrition support to central government and donor-funded projects in private and public sectors, supporting project startups, establishing and updating institutional operations systems, developing annual work plans and strategic implementation approaches, providing support supervision to a multicultural staff, developing systems to evaluate project performance, and providing appropriate intervention approaches thus improving on results and positive impacts. Immaculate holds MSc in Applied Human Nutrition from University of Nairobi in Kenya.

SELECTED PROFESSIONAL HISTORY

Programme Manager Agri-Nutrition, January 2016 to present

Coordinator and National convener, Kenya National Food Consumption Survey. Coordinate and support implementation of food and nutrition security at National level covering 47 counties in Kenya. Support the development of nutrition policies, guidelines, and Implementation strategies in the country such as Agri-nutrition resource manual currently under use, contributed to documenting Kenya Food Composition Tables, Agri-nutrition Framework development and Kenya National Nutrition Plan of Action. Working through technical working groups to plan and execute nutrition activities.

Consultant on Food and Nutrition security /WASH USAID-KAVES Feed the Future Project, January 2015 – 20116. Responsible for overall strategic planning, coordination, implementation, monitoring and evaluations, and other operations management of five-year integrated productivity, poverty reduction, food security and nutrition program. Provides financial oversight of the budget, ensuring compliance with donor regulations and supervising regional

operations. Uses behavior change communications strategies adapting to healthier behaviors. Closely coordinated with component leads to ensure project beneficiaries receive a holistic package of technical assistance in agricultural production, increased production and demand for nutritious foods and natural resource management. Managed a transparent sub award system for activities implemented by local partner organizations. Conducted regular visits to partner organizations to review financial management and monitoring and evaluation data, and formed recommendations for correction on implementation issues.

Represented USAID/KAVES at government, donor, NGO and other relevant events, in close coordination with the Chief of Party, Deputy Chief of Party and country leadership in and outside Kenya with success.

Senior Technical Advisor – Nutrition, PATH KENYA-APHIAplus, USAID PEPFAR project June 2010 to December 2014.

Provided technical support on health and nutrition to a multi-component programs focused on food security, health and improved nutrition outcomes. Trained project staff and local partner organizations in both countries in food security, social behavior change communication and agrinutrition.

Established 250 mother to mother support groups in Nyanza and Western Provinces to educate communities on Infant and Young child Nutrition resulting to;

- Improved community access to nutrition information, education and counseling.
- Improved community lifestyle and reduced morbidity.
- Improved Exclusive breastfeeding by 25%, food security by 32%, and women dietary diversity by 45% from 4.1 to 6.2 food groups.
- Collaborated extensively with partners to improve health care workers capacity to provide adequate nutrition services to clients.

Provincial Nutrition Officer, Nairobi, Ministry of Health, July 2005 to June 2011

As nutrition team leader, collaborated extensively with interdisciplinary care team to meet the nutritional needs of each resident. Worked with various sectors and partners within the Kenya Government, to provide technical support on nutrition education, counseling and support for PLHIV, Prevention of Mother to Child Transmission of HIV/AIDS, Infant and Young Child Feeding/Maternal Nutrition and Integrated of Acute Malnutrition. Coordinated nutrition care with other members of the health care team and delegated responsibilities. Provided collaboration between Ministry of health and other partners on a number of nutrition related initiatives including the design and development of National guideline/strategy on Nutrition and HIV/AIDS, communication strategy on Infant and Young Child Feeding, Micronutrients deficiency control programme, Integrated Management of Acute Malnutrition and National School health Policy and Strategy.

Emergency Nutrition Technical Advisor, UNICEF KCO January 1997 to June 2005

Carried out nutrition assessments and analysis and established healthful and therapeutic meal plans and menus in the wards using locally available foods and nutritional supplements. Provided technical support and guidance to ministry of health and partners in handling malnutrition cases at facility level and community level including coordination of district-level stakeholders' meetings. Established UNICEF project sites and addressed Nutrition issues that needed support, reported to both Ministry of health and UNICEF office. Devised meal plans in line with patients' age, gender, diagnosis, cultural background and religious practices in hospitals. Encouraged clients and caregivers to follow recommended food guidelines for well-balanced diets. Maintained up-to-date knowledge about the latest research and on malnutrition trends in Garrisa, Marsabit, Isiolo and Wajir.

EDUCATION

MSc, Applied Human Nutrition, University of Nairobi, Kenya, 2005.

BSc, Home-Economics, Food and Nutrition, University of Eastern Africa, Baraton, Eldoret, Kenya, 1994.

Certificate Course Leadership and Management 2014

Publications:

Nyaugo IA, et.al: Kenya Food Composition Tables 2018. Kenya Food Recipes 2018

Nyaugo IA, et.al: A Resource Manual for Agri-Nutrition in Kenya 2017

Nyaugo IA, et.al: Kenya National Nutrition Action Plan

Referees:

- I. Veronica Kirogo Head, Nutrition and Dietetics Unit, Ministry of Health. Email: virimu.kirogo@gmail.com Tel: 0721434443.
- 2. Dr. Steve New, Chief of Party, USAID-KAVES. Email: snew@fintrac.com Tel: 0715818988.
- 3. Dr. James Mukabi, Chief of Party, USAID-Aphiaplus Project. Email: jmukabi@apth.org Tel: 0722565432